{
  "reference_number": "11278",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Why wait? We have known about climate change for many years now and we have been asleep on the job. We need to act now."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "We need to be talking about the elephant in the room - and addressing the impact of animal agriculture on the climate and\n environment. Failing to do so just makes it look like the Govt is in cahoots with farmers, at the expense of the environment and we\n\n have seen more than enough of that already. I am sick to death of NZ clinging to old ways of an economy based on primary industries.\n We used to be a country of pioneers and innovators. Yet our reliance on animal industries generally hasn't changed for a century. NZ\n\n is so much more than a country of sheep and beef farmers, yet we can't seem to move beyond that archaic identity."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, of course we should be open to revision if things change, but that change shouldn't be backing off or weakening of our\n commitment to halt climate change - it's not as if we have a back up plan for when we destroy this environment."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No and yes. I would like to see more budgets set, but given the lack of government action to date, I believe three budgets are an\n\n adequate (if somewhat disappointing) starting point."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Again - change should only be an increase in commitment, not a backing off."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Yes and no. I agree the Government should take into consideration scientific and technological changes. But economic, fiscal, social\n\nand energy considerations ought to only be secondary considerations because those elements will suffer anyway if we do not\naddress climate change. We might have to accept that years of apathy and a cavalier attitude towards our environment has put us in\n\nour current position and we might have to accept that it is now a case of 'short term pain for long term gain'."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Governments are notorious for being all talk and no walk. Setting timeframes introduces some accountability. Lead by example."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The number one impact on climate change is animal agriculture. The Government needs to grow a spine and address this.\n\nPussyfooting around the topic, concentrating on strawman issues (anything but farming) might placate the farming community but it\nonly disappoints and irritates non-farmers and endangers our combined futures and sustainability."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "The CCC should be empowered to make its own decisions. Advice to governments takes too long and is easily ignored. Climate\n\nchange is here, now. Act on it!"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Governments of the world might have left it too late - we might not have any choice but to adapt to climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Please address the number one climate change impactor - animal agriculture. \"We are, quite literally, gambling with the future of our\n\nplanet- for the sake of hamburgers\" - Peter Singer."
    }
  ]
}
